<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>self-improvement on Antonio Martinović blog</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/tags/self-improvement/</link><description>Recent content in self-improvement on Antonio Martinović blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</managingEditor><webMaster>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</webMaster><copyright>Copyright 2023 by Antonio Martinović</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://martinovic.blog/tags/self-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Week 2: Slower second week but still building pace</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/week-2-slowdown-but-still-strong/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/week-2-slowdown-but-still-strong/</guid><description>&lt;p>The second week started of slow with some very small commits, it was about
fixing up the Zitadel demo I started, which, to be honest, was only broken
because I didn&amp;rsquo;t read the documentation properly. Ahh yes, the famous dilemma,
should I spend 3 hours with try different random things or should I spend 30
minutes reading the docs? I think we all know the answer to that one. RTFM, but
hey, at least I got to learn a bit more about the Zitadel API.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Next up were some tiny changes to RSS feed on this bug, there was some Mastodon
about whether to keep the full content of the post in the feed or just the
summary, it ended up being that most people want the full thing, so I&amp;rsquo;ve added
that in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The last thing I worked on was on the &lt;a href="https://payloadcms.com/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Payload
&lt;/a>
demo,
I&amp;rsquo;ve added a few collections and generated fixture or database see to make
development easier, and I&amp;rsquo;ve started adding some actually frontend to it, again,
based on &lt;a href="https://nextjs.org/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
NextJS
&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://tailwindcss.com/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Tailwind CSS
&lt;/a>
, good old web development.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Week 1: Back to coding</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/week-1-consistent-coding/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/week-1-consistent-coding/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="the-problem">The problem
&lt;a href="#the-problem" class="anchor"> &lt;svg fill="#444444" width="16" height="16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-link-45deg" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
&lt;path d="M4.715 6.542 3.343 7.914a3 3 0 1 0 4.243 4.243l1.828-1.829A3 3 0 0 0 8.586 5.5L8 6.086a1.002 1.002 0 0 0-.154.199 2 2 0 0 1 .861 3.337L6.88 11.45a2 2 0 1 1-2.83-2.83l.793-.792a4.018 4.018 0 0 1-.128-1.287z"/>
&lt;path d="M6.586 4.672A3 3 0 0 0 7.414 9.5l.775-.776a2 2 0 0 1-.896-3.346L9.12 3.55a2 2 0 1 1 2.83 2.83l-.793.792c.112.42.155.855.128 1.287l1.372-1.372a3 3 0 1 0-4.243-4.243L6.586 4.672z"/>
&lt;/svg> &lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Ever since my role changed from a software engineer to a engineering manager,
I&amp;rsquo;ve been coding far less, my contributions were mostly in the form of code
reviews and the occasional bug fix, and this has fueled a feeling of longing to
actually write code again, to be able to create something from scratch. I&amp;rsquo;ve
been thinking about this for a while. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try and do something about
it.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="the-solution">The solution
&lt;a href="#the-solution" class="anchor"> &lt;svg fill="#444444" width="16" height="16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-link-45deg" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
&lt;path d="M4.715 6.542 3.343 7.914a3 3 0 1 0 4.243 4.243l1.828-1.829A3 3 0 0 0 8.586 5.5L8 6.086a1.002 1.002 0 0 0-.154.199 2 2 0 0 1 .861 3.337L6.88 11.45a2 2 0 1 1-2.83-2.83l.793-.792a4.018 4.018 0 0 1-.128-1.287z"/>
&lt;path d="M6.586 4.672A3 3 0 0 0 7.414 9.5l.775-.776a2 2 0 0 1-.896-3.346L9.12 3.55a2 2 0 1 1 2.83 2.83l-.793.792c.112.42.155.855.128 1.287l1.372-1.372a3 3 0 1 0-4.243-4.243L6.586 4.672z"/>
&lt;/svg> &lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to try and do at least 1 commit every day, this is a small
experiment to see if I can get back into the habit of coding, and to see if I
can actually do it every day and to keep myself a bit more accountable, I&amp;rsquo;ll be
posting weekly updates on my blog here. This comes from the personal learnings
of the last few years that I have spent reading through various books. One of
the most influential ones
was &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Atomic Habits
&lt;/a>
by James Clear, which
I highly recommend, it&amp;rsquo;s a book that has a lot of actionable advice on how to
build habits and how to break bad ones.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This brings me to this little personal experiment and a few of the rules I&amp;rsquo;ve
set for myself:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>At least 1 commit every day&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is no minimum size for the commit, simple documentation changes are
just fine&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The commit can be in any project, personal or open source (here&amp;rsquo;s hopping I
can get myself involved more in open source)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;h1 id="so-what-did-i-do-this-week">So what did I do this week?
&lt;a href="#so-what-did-i-do-this-week" class="anchor"> &lt;svg fill="#444444" width="16" height="16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-link-45deg" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
&lt;path d="M4.715 6.542 3.343 7.914a3 3 0 1 0 4.243 4.243l1.828-1.829A3 3 0 0 0 8.586 5.5L8 6.086a1.002 1.002 0 0 0-.154.199 2 2 0 0 1 .861 3.337L6.88 11.45a2 2 0 1 1-2.83-2.83l.793-.792a4.018 4.018 0 0 1-.128-1.287z"/>
&lt;path d="M6.586 4.672A3 3 0 0 0 7.414 9.5l.775-.776a2 2 0 0 1-.896-3.346L9.12 3.55a2 2 0 1 1 2.83 2.83l-.793.792c.112.42.155.855.128 1.287l1.372-1.372a3 3 0 1 0-4.243-4.243L6.586 4.672z"/>
&lt;/svg> &lt;/a>
&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>It has mainly been about some demo projects utilising various new web
application development technologies, well not new per se, but certainly new to
me. These
were &lt;a href="https://nextjs.org/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
NextJS
&lt;/a>
, &lt;a href="https://tailwindcss.com/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Tailwind CSS
&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://fly.io"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Fly.io
&lt;/a>
. Some CMSs like &lt;a href="https://strapi.io/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Strapi
&lt;/a>
and &lt;a href="https://payloadcms.com/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Payload
&lt;/a>
, which might or might not feed into
another project in the future. I&amp;rsquo;ve also been investigating a new auth
system &lt;a href="https://zitadel.com"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Zitadel
&lt;/a>
which is showing a lot of promise for a
small new startup. And I&amp;rsquo;ve also updated the Hugo
theme &lt;a href="https://github.com/TopHatCroat/izi-hugo-theme/"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
izi
&lt;/a>
used by this blog by
doing some RSS bug fixes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s it for this week, it&amp;rsquo;s not much but it&amp;rsquo;s honest work. Looking forward to
giving a week 2 update.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why I stopped learning</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 years ago when I finished university I was learning something new every day, I
was a software engineer and there was, what seemed to be an ocean of new shiny
technology I wanted to learn about, things that make the application run faster,
or UI look nicer, things that make the developer experience better.
I moved from one company to another always jumping into a more interesting
project, always being able to benefit from the things I’ve learnt before,
finding niche and not so niche areas to improve the new code and the product I
found myself working on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And it worked for a while, and then I got an offer to lead a team of developers,
I took it, of course, because that’s what your next career step is, right?
Right?
No, it’s really not, but I didn’t know that at the time.
Anyway, this is a big change, we are not talking about another programming
language or another framework here, it’s a completely different set of skills,
and more importantly, values that I need to live now.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-it-happened">How it happened
&lt;a href="#how-it-happened" class="anchor"> &lt;svg fill="#444444" width="16" height="16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-link-45deg" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
&lt;path d="M4.715 6.542 3.343 7.914a3 3 0 1 0 4.243 4.243l1.828-1.829A3 3 0 0 0 8.586 5.5L8 6.086a1.002 1.002 0 0 0-.154.199 2 2 0 0 1 .861 3.337L6.88 11.45a2 2 0 1 1-2.83-2.83l.793-.792a4.018 4.018 0 0 1-.128-1.287z"/>
&lt;path d="M6.586 4.672A3 3 0 0 0 7.414 9.5l.775-.776a2 2 0 0 1-.896-3.346L9.12 3.55a2 2 0 1 1 2.83 2.83l-.793.792c.112.42.155.855.128 1.287l1.372-1.372a3 3 0 1 0-4.243-4.243L6.586 4.672z"/>
&lt;/svg> &lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This clarity of knowing exactly what I need to learn next, which was in plain
sight at the start of one’s career, and sense of progress is exactly what
motivated me and helped me greatly in achieving learning goals.
However, when I moved into a more management focused role, it was the first time
in my life that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know exactly what to learn about next, I had very
little people experience and no idea of what I need to know about to become a
good team lead or engineering manager or however you like to call it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Not having a well defined goal, makes every self-improvement attempt much less
effective and enjoyable, it starts making it feel like a chore, something you
have to do to achieve something, but you are not sure exactly what, or are you
even going in the right direction.
If this persists a person will slowly invest less and less time into learning,
probably the most evil thing about it is that it creeps in slowly, which makes
it hard to notice, it’s something to do with frogs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What helped me realise that this was happening to me was that I found myself
struggling to focus, I would rarely get in the flow, and I started looking
forward to not doing anything on the weekend a bit more than before.
Don’t get me wrong, not doing anything over the weekend is amazing and I
recommend it wholeheartedly, but I knew that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t who I was every weekend.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="regaining-my-drive">Regaining My Drive
&lt;a href="#regaining-my-drive" class="anchor"> &lt;svg fill="#444444" width="16" height="16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" class="bi bi-link-45deg" viewBox="0 0 16 16">
&lt;path d="M4.715 6.542 3.343 7.914a3 3 0 1 0 4.243 4.243l1.828-1.829A3 3 0 0 0 8.586 5.5L8 6.086a1.002 1.002 0 0 0-.154.199 2 2 0 0 1 .861 3.337L6.88 11.45a2 2 0 1 1-2.83-2.83l.793-.792a4.018 4.018 0 0 1-.128-1.287z"/>
&lt;path d="M6.586 4.672A3 3 0 0 0 7.414 9.5l.775-.776a2 2 0 0 1-.896-3.346L9.12 3.55a2 2 0 1 1 2.83 2.83l-.793.792c.112.42.155.855.128 1.287l1.372-1.372a3 3 0 1 0-4.243-4.243L6.586 4.672z"/>
&lt;/svg> &lt;/a>
&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Getting back on track is not an easy process and, much like it went away,
getting back takes time.
It requires self-reflection to identify the source of problem.
What often seems to be the case is that the cheese has been moved, as stated in
the famous
book &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4894.Who_Moved_My_Cheese"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Who Moved My Chese
&lt;/a>
,
and we don&amp;rsquo;t realise it.
This is what happened to me, it can come in different forms to each person, for
me it was that even though my job description changed by quite a bit, I did not
adapt my learning direction and just kept learning as if what I am doing is
still individual contribution, I saw that I needed to change that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Trying to optimise your learning path, like picking the best resources only, is
not something you should be overthinking, it’s a sort
of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bin_packing_problem"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
bin packing problem
&lt;/a>
,
but with time and it’s virtually impossible to have an optimal progression path.
What is important is that what you learn you can immediately try out, not only
will this ensure the lessons stick, but it will also give a huge motivation
boost to keep at it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To conclude, what I changed was I realised the immense value of the new position
I found myself in being able to do much more with a team then I can do on my on,
in hindsight, I can’t believe I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it sooner.
Some take a more drastic approach, I know a person who quit a very well paid job
to instead spend a year learning ML and AI, simply because he was not feeling
motivated to work and he realised he didn’t want his whole life to feel like a
chore because of it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To conclude, if you are not feeling motivated to keep learning about whatever it
is you do, you need to change something, either your approach, or what you do.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Try to take it easy</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</guid><description>&lt;p>I think that we all want to be good people who try to be nice and help others
even though the today’s world makes it seem like this is not the case.
I try to make others’ lives easier by being respectful of their time and not
asking for much of their attention because I know they are busy people with a
bunch of stuff on their minds.
But then I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself asking, why am I so often not giving the same
treatment to myself.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Speaking out of my own previous experience, my plans and aspirations were very
ambitious, but I did not reach the goals that I’ve set for myself, I thought
it&amp;rsquo;s because I’m lazy, or because I’m not good enough, but that&amp;rsquo;s not it.
No one wants to work too much, and working too long tends to produce very
diminishing returns as the focus and effectiveness of my work slips, my
creativity suffers and, in my opinion, along with time, creativity my most
valuable resource as an individual.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What helped me arrive to this conclusion was what I read in a book
&lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6452796-drive"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Drive by Daniel H. Pink
&lt;/a>
which talks about motivation and how to create an environment that nurtures it,
mostly from an organisation’s perspective, but it can be applied to leading
ourselves as well.
It&amp;rsquo;s an excellent and concise book which I wholeheartedly recommend.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As much as we would like to be incredibly efficient and productive, humans are
simply not, and the solution is definitely not to push are selves to the point
of burning out, you are not a lesser person for allowing yourself to take it a
bit easier.
That&amp;rsquo;s why I started reducing the amount of things on my plate and I think you
should consider it as well. There are real benefits to taking the time to rest,
recharge and refocus and there are others
&lt;a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/01/06/how-slowing-down-at-work-can-help-you-get-more-done.html"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
who agree with this
&lt;/a>
.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This definitely doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean reducing my ultimate aspirations or accepting that
I will not achieve what I want, on the contrary, this means to actually allow
myself to focus on the few things I have happening in my life currently so that
I ensure I give it my full attention and, more importantly, finish those things
before moving on to the next one (or quitting because I realise I don&amp;rsquo;t actually
want it that much, but don&amp;rsquo;t use it as an excuse).
It is even not counter-intuitive once I understood that one of the biggest time
wasters I have, and I have more than enough of those, is the constant context
switching that just disappears when there is fewer things going on at once.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There is a bazillion of people wrote and talked about this topic on the
internet, good and bad (like this blog post)that there is a lot of other
resources you can find on how taking a lighter approach ultimately allows us to
achieve bigger results.
If you want to see more of it I recommend this excellent talk with plenty of
other good
ideas: &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/FS1mnISoG7U"
target="_blank"
rel="noopener">
Scaling Yourself by Scott Hanselman
&lt;/a>
&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>