<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://martinovic.blog/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why I stopped learning</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</guid><description>5 years ago when I finished university I was learning something new every day, I was a software engineer and there was, what seemed to be an ocean of new shiny technology I wanted to learn about, things that make the application run faster, or UI look nicer, things that make the developer experience better. I moved from one company to another always jumping into a more interesting project, always being able to benefit from the things I’ve learnt before, finding niche and not so niche areas to improve the new code and the product I found myself working on.</description></item><item><title>Improvement days</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/improvement-days/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/improvement-days/</guid><description>Improvement day(s) is an event in which each team member is given a chance to use the day(s) in whichever way they want, well as long as it’s something productive, where are not here for improving Tekken or Rocket League skills on the PlayStation. What we are about here is different things like learning something new, trying out a new library or tool and even hacking out a tiny proof of concept.</description></item><item><title>Try to take it easy</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</guid><description>I think that we all want to be good people who try to be nice and help others even though the today’s world makes it seem like this is not the case. I try to make others’ lives easier by being respectful of their time and not asking for much of their attention because I know they are busy people with a bunch of stuff on their minds. But then I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself asking, why am I so often not giving the same treatment to myself.</description></item><item><title>Setup Elasticsearch on CircleCI</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/circle-ci-elasticsearh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/circle-ci-elasticsearh/</guid><description>This is going to be a short one I&amp;rsquo;m only writing this one because I could not Google exactly what I needed as easily as I expected, so hopefully it might help someone. Setting up an Elasticsearch instance to test against on CircleCI is actually quite straightforward.
Your .circleci/config.yml should look something like this:
jobs: build: docker: - image: circleci/&amp;lt;language&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;version TAG&amp;gt; - image: docker.elastic.co/elasticsearch/elasticsearch:7.12.0 #1 environment: - transport.host: localhost #2 - network.</description></item><item><title>Merge Two History tables</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/merge-history-table-migration/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/merge-history-table-migration/</guid><description>History tables hold the past state of an entity by saving all the values of the original entity along with a date and time range field that specify when these values were valid, I will refer to this field as &amp;ldquo;validity&amp;rdquo;. This pattern is used when you need to remember the changes an entity went through over time, it is often used with, for example, pricing data, so that you can track changes of some price as time passes.</description></item><item><title>Home .git</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/home-git/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/home-git/</guid><description>Git is an incredibly useful tool for a programmer, you use it to version the work you do and distribute it easily on other computers. But over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve found that a lot of my workflow depends on various configurations and helper scripts I have in my path. So why not version those as well, it does allow you to get started in seconds in a very familiar environment on every new computer or even a server if you spend a lot of your time in SSH sessions.</description></item><item><title>KDE Connect commands</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/kdeconnect-commands/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/kdeconnect-commands/</guid><description>KDE Connect useful commands So I&amp;rsquo;ve been using KDE Connect Android application for a while now due to its great integration KDE Plasma desktop. It allows you to send files over, share your clipboard, sync notifications and has other useful features like remote control using the phones screen as a touchpad or keyboard on your computer which is greatly appreciated feature for when you just couldn&amp;rsquo;t be asked to reach for your mouse to select the next YouTube video to play.</description></item><item><title>Hello world</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/helloworld/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/helloworld/</guid><description>Well, hello there Welcome to my blog, this is going to be a place for me to share what and how I use in my work and at home. Stuff like mini tutorials, random rants and TILs of programming.
Stay tuned!</description></item></channel></rss>