<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>productivity on Antonio Martinović blog</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in productivity on Antonio Martinović blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><managingEditor>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</managingEditor><webMaster>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</webMaster><copyright>Copyright 2023 by Antonio Martinović</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://martinovic.blog/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why I stopped learning</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/why-i-stopped-learning/</guid><description>5 years ago when I finished university I was learning something new every day, I was a software engineer and there was, what seemed to be an ocean of new shiny technology I wanted to learn about, things that make the application run faster, or UI look nicer, things that make the developer experience better. I moved from one company to another always jumping into a more interesting project, always being able to benefit from the things I’ve learnt before, finding niche and not so niche areas to improve the new code and the product I found myself working on.</description></item><item><title>Improvement days</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/improvement-days/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/improvement-days/</guid><description>Improvement day(s) is an event in which each team member is given a chance to use the day(s) in whichever way they want, well as long as it’s something productive, where are not here for improving Tekken or Rocket League skills on the PlayStation. What we are about here is different things like learning something new, trying out a new library or tool and even hacking out a tiny proof of concept.</description></item><item><title>Try to take it easy</title><link>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>martinovic.antonio@gmail.com (Antonio Martinović)</author><guid>https://martinovic.blog/posts/try-to-take-it-easy/</guid><description>I think that we all want to be good people who try to be nice and help others even though the today’s world makes it seem like this is not the case. I try to make others’ lives easier by being respectful of their time and not asking for much of their attention because I know they are busy people with a bunch of stuff on their minds. But then I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself asking, why am I so often not giving the same treatment to myself.</description></item></channel></rss>